The Lost Vikings
Copyright (C) 1992-2014 Blizzard Entertainment
For EULA see file "Lost Vikings EULA txt 20140331.txt"
======================================================

The Vikings' Story
------------------
It was a day that the members of the Viking village looked forward to every year. On this day everyone in the village celebrated the fall harvest with contests of bravery and skill throughout the afternoon followed by a grand feast at dusk.

The most anticipated event of the day was the hunt. In this competition, the best huntsmen from the village venture into the wilderness to see who could catch the most game for the evening's feast. By noon, all the participants had arrived at the  starting point of the hunt, except for three Vikings who lived just outside the village. Since their tardiness was nothing new, the decision was made to start the hunt without them. Upon hearing the horn, indicating the beginning of the competition, Olaf the Stout and his two buddies, Baleog the Fierce and Erik the Swift simply rushed into the forest to prevent the others from having too great of a head start.

Meanwhile, the infamous intergalactic zookeeper, Tomator, piloted his space craft to Earth through a fiery vortex that appeared high above the fjords of the Baltic Sea. Tomator was sure that he could find adequate specimens for his zoo on this tiny planet. He commanded his ship to begin its descent as he made preparations to go on a hunt of his own.

As Olaf the Stout, Baleog the Fierce and Erik the Swift walked home from the feast they were still bragging over their triumphs in the hunt. When each brother had finished claiming that he was a better hunter than the other two, they retired to their cottages, oblivious to the strange flying object that had appeared directly over their village.

Tomator brought his craft closer to the ground, trying to locate the three specimens that he had previously chosen. He had noticed them earlier, when they appeared to be the victors of some primitive ritual of skill and strength. After a few minutes, Tomator's computer located the selected humans and began to teleport his unsuspecting captives aboard his ship.

Erik, the swiftest of the Vikings, was awakened suddenly to find himself suspended above his bed and being pulled upward. Despite his efforts to resist, he was drawn through the top of his hut and into the night sky. Next, Olaf the Stout and Baleog the Fierce experienced the same fate as they too were pulled from their beds, toward the strange metallic object in the sky.

With the acquisition complete, Tomator took his craft out of orbit. Due to a short circuit during the teleportation process, the Vikings materialized in the corridors of Tomator's ship rather than in his specimen room. Now the Vikings only hope to return home is the use of their skills and the strange vortices that can carry them through time and space.

Your story begins with the three Lost Vikings aboard Tomator's ship, and only with your help and expertise can they find their way back home again.

You must guide the Lost Vikings through the complex maze of Tomator's space craft. Use Erik's speed, Baleog's weaponry and Olaf''s defensive abilities to help return these poor lost souls to their village.


How to Play
-----------
The goal of The Lost Vikings is to help Olaf the Stout, Baleog the Fierce and Erik the Swift find their way back home. To do so they must successfully solve all the levels of the game going through time and space to many different eras, until they confront and defeat their captor, Tomator.

To successfully complete a level all three Vikings must get to the "EXIT" alive. They will then continue onto the next level. At the end of the last level of each era there will be a vortex that will warp the Vikings to the next era in time.

Each Viking starts each level with three health points and no items. These health points can be lost either one at a time or all at once depending on what type of enemy or obstacle does damage to the character. The health status of each warrior is represented by the three red dots under their picture in the status bar at the top of the screen. Health points can be restored by eating food that can be found throughout the game. They can also use armor to get a bonus health point represented by a blue dot.

To complete the level the Vikings will have to use their skills in many different ways to solve the puzzles. Many times the Vikings will have to use their skills cooperatively.

When the Vikings get to a new level you will be given a password. Write this down in the back of this manual. You will be able to restart the game later by using this password. If at any time a Viking has died or you feel that they are stuck in a position making the level unsolvable, you can give up by pressing a PAUSE key and then selecting YES. Doing this will bring all dead Vikings back to life and they will restart the level.

There are many hidden places throughout the game. If the Vikings find these places, they are sure to find something valuable.

In the early levels there will be hint buttons with '?' in them. When a Viking is near one of these you can press the S key to get a hint.


Keyboard Controls
-----------------
Alt-Enter								
TOGGLE FULLSCREEN AND WINDOW MODE

Alt-F4									
QUIT APPLICATION

Left/Right Arrow Keys or Keypad 4/6  	
MOVES THE VIKING LEFT OR RIGHT

Up/Down Arrow Keys or Keypad 5 or 8/2 	
MOVES THE VIKING UP OR DOWN
When a Viking is on a ladder or an elevator, these will move the Viking in that direction.

F Key, Space, Enter, Keypad Enter, Keypad (+)	
PERFORMS A VIKING'S PRIMARY ABILITY.
Baleog the Fierce will swing his mighty sword.
Erik the Swift will jump to great heights.
Olaf the Stout will raise or lower his shield.

D Key 									
PERFORMS A VIKING'S SECONDARY ABILITY.
Baleog the Fierce will shoot arrows with his bow.
Erik the Swift uses his head to bash while running.
Olaf the Stout will raise or lower his shield.

E Key 									
USE AN ITEM
Allows a Viking to use the highlighted item from his supply of items.

S Key 									
ACTIVATES a SWITCH
Allows a Viking to activate buttons, flip switches, etc. and talk to other characters.

Ctrl, Keypad 7, Keypad 9, Keypad 0		
SWITCHES VIKINGS
Will enable the player to take control of one of the other two Vikings.

Esc Key, P Key 							
PAUSES THE GAME
Pressing one of these keys during play will pause the game. When the game is paused you will be given the option to GIVE UP? Choosing YES will restart you at the beginning of the same level. Choosing NO will resume the game. The GIVE UP option is very useful if one of your Vikings has died or are in a position so that you cannot complete the level. You cannot complete the level if a Viking has died.

Tab Key, Caps Lock						
SELECTS AN ITEM
Allows you to choose the item to be used. To choose an item, press one of these buttons and move the flashing box to the desired item. Pressing the button again will resume the game. This can also be used to pause the game.

Alt-S 									
SOUND
Turns the sound off, pressing the buttons again turns the sound back on.

Alt-M 									
MUSIC
Turns the music off, pressing the buttons again turns the music back on.


Items
-----
Throughout the course of the game, there will be several different items that will assist you in completing the game.
Food--Heals 1 one health point
Steaks--Heals 2 health points
Shield--Gives a Viking a bonus blue health point
Bombs--You can drop them anywhere you like to blow something up
Smart Bombs--Destroys all enemies on the screen
Flaming Arrow--Kills an enemy in one shot
Keys--Used to unlock doors of the same color
Gravity Boots--Lets a Viking walk in a gravitational field
Buttons--Used in many places to activate things in the game, like opening doors
Switches--Also used in many places to activate things in the game such as opening doors
Target--Acts like a button but must be shot by Baelog to activate


Inventory Control
-----------------
Each Viking has the ability to carry up to four items. An item is automatically picked up when they touch it (as long as the Viking has room to carry the item). To use an item, press a SELECT key and move the flashing box to the desired item. Then press a SELECT key again to resume your game. You can then press E at anytime to use the selected item.

The Vikings are also able to trade items with each other, but only if they are close to each other. To trade an item you must first switch control to the Viking with the item you want to trade. Press a SELECT key, move the flashing box to the desired item to be traded and press a Primary Ability key. Then move the item to the Viking you want to give the item to and press a Primary Ability key. To exit inventory mode, press a SELECT key.

You can also throw away food or bombs by moving the item to the trash can.


Saving the Game
---------------
The Lost Vikings allows you to continue where you last left off by entering a password. The game will give you a password at the beginning of each new level you reach. In case you forget to write down the password at the start of a new level, you can retrieve the password again by pressing D, E or S at the funeral screen.

Erik, Olaf, and Baleog want to remind you to write down your passwords on the page provided in the back of this manual. This way you will always know where it is and you will never have to replay levels that you have already completed.

To start the game from a saved password, select PASSWORD from the START screen. Enter your password by using the Up and Down Arrow Keys or type it in for faster entry. If you type the password in, it will automatically go to the next letter, if you are using the arrow keys, then use the Right Arrow Key to move to the next letter.  If you have made a mistake in the password, use the Left Arrow Key or Backspace to undo the error.


Character Profiles
-------------------
Name: Erik the Swift
Age: 19
Height: 5'8"
Weight: 160 lbs.
Specialty: Scouting, speeding
Equipment: Running shoes, a strong head
Occupation: Mercenary, track coach, stuntman, pizza delivery
Hobbies: Sprinting, rock climbing
Favorite Authors: Dr. Seuss, Friedrich Nietzsche
Favorite Movies: The Running Man, Running Scared, Run Silent, Run Deep, Logan's Run, Running on Empty, Nuns on the Run, Running Brave, Erik the Viking
Favorite band: Rush
Favorite Meal: Fast food
Ailments: Athlete's foot, frequent headaches
Favorite Pets: Cheetahs, jaguars, falcons
Desired Birthday Present: A football helmet
Favorite Holiday:  Groundhog Day
Favorite Quote: "It is better to run and jump away from enemies than it is to let them smash you into little pieces." - Anonymous
Comments: The tactical genius and self-proclaimed leader of the party.
Erik is the swiftest and most agile of the Vikings which makes him an indispensable part of any expedition. His wit and resourcefulness are often key to resolving difficult situations. However, he has a short attention span and gets easily agitated by sitting in the same place too long. In fact, his patience is often times too thin to tolerate his two brothers. Despite these shortcomings, he proves to be a valuable companion on any adventure.
Strengths: Erik is the swiftest Viking. He can outrun any enemy and leap high into the air. He also has a head of stone which he can use to bash open walls.
Weaknesses: Erik has no defensive capabilities, which leaves him very vulnerable if he goes out scouting by himself. His speed can also be a liability at times if you are not careful.

Name: Baleog the Fierce
Age: 25
Height: 6'0"
Weight: 220 lbs.
Specialty: Combat, chopping, slicing and dicing.
Equipment: Bow, arrows, sword, attitude
Occupation: Mercenary, corporate raider
Hobbies: Body building, knife throwing, bowling
Favorite Drink: Fruit punch
Preferred Vegetable: Squash
Goals: World domination, bowling league champion
Favorite Movies: Sparticus, Rambo II, Conan the Barbarian, Pumping Iron, The Terminator
Favorite Exclamation: Yo!
Favorite Vacation Spot: Iceland
Favorite Vowel: A
Favorite Holiday: Labor Day
Favorite Band: Aerosmith
Favorite Quote: "Enter the mill and you will come out floury and
baked." - unknown Danish baker
Prized Possessions: Sword-shaped letter opener, long underwear
Comments: Baleog's enormous ego is tolerable only in light of the martial skill he provides to the expedition. When he's not accusing his brothers of being lazy or weak, Baleog can often be found sharpening his sword and contemplating his strategy for world conquest. Nonetheless, despite his sometimes less than pleasant company, Baleog is a fierce foe to any that stand in a party's way.
Strengths: Baleog can attack with his sword and shoot arrows. He can also use arrows to activate switches that are a long distance away.
Weaknesses: He has not yet mastered the art of defense. Therefore he usually hides behind Olaf's shield during battles with formidable foes.

Name: Olaf the Stout
Age: 23
Height: 6' 2"
Weight: 320 lbs.
Specialty: Defense, aeronautics, comedic relief
Equipment: Shield, belly, a silly laugh
Occupation: Mercenary, Winchell's poster boy
Hobbies: Para-Sailing, bungee jumping
Favorite Food: Meatloaf, sprinkled doughnuts
Ultimate Fantasy: To be a Sumo wrestler
Favorite Instrument: Tuba
Favorite Movies: Fat Man and Little Boy, Little Big Man, Breakfast at Tiffany's, The Breakfast Club, The Naked Lunch, Lunch Wagon, Dinner at Eight, Guess Who's Coming to Dinner, My Dinner with Andre
Favorite Relative: Uncle Beorn
Favorite Holiday: Thanksgiving Day
Favorite Books: ABC-123, Green Eggs and Ham
Favorite Quote: "Life is just a big banana. Be careful not to slip on the peel and all will turn out fine." - Uncle Beorn
Family: Married with two children
Favorite Toy: Yellow rubber duck named Elvis
Comments: This jovial Viking, with his hardy constitution and
steadfast resolve, can be counted on in any situation. His appetite for adventure is rivaled only by his passion for pastries. Unfortunately, he is often seized by unprovoked laughing fits, making extended travel with him somewhat tiresome. His hulking presence is, however, greatly appreciated in the heat of battle.
Strengths: He can use his shield to block enemies and their shots. He can also hold his shield above his head and float long distances, which gives him great maneuverability.
Weaknesses: He has to wait for Baleog in combat situations and his shield can not always protect him and the other Vikings from certain foes that have jumping capabilities of their own.

CREDITS
-------
GAME DESIGN 
Blizzard Entertainment 

PRODUCERS
Allen Adham & Alan Pavlish

ASSISTANT PRODUCER
Steve Nguyen

EXECUTIVE PRODUCER
Brian Fargo

LEVEL DESIGN
Ronald Miller

PROGRAMMING
Michael Morhaime, Frank Pearce & Allen Adham

PC PROGRAMMING
Bryan Waters

ADDITIONAL PROGRAMMING
Patrick Wyatt, Jim Sproul

ARTWORK
Joeyray Hall, Ronald Millar, Samwise Didier, Clyde Matsumoto, Jason Magness

ADDITIONAL ARTWORK
Stu Rose, Todd Camasta, Cheryl Austin, Spencer Kipe

SOUND & MUSIC
Allister Brimble, Dave Bean, Alan Premselaar, Glenn Stafford, Rick Jackson

PC CONVERSION
David Givone

PC CONVERSION QA
Danny H. Nguyen
Jason Kwan
Matthew Grubb

SPEICIAL THANKS TO
The DOSBox team 
